Guide to the Eleze McKenzie collection of medieval manuscript leaves, ca. 1150-1840
McKenzie, Eleze collection of Medieval and Renaissance manuscript leaves
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Eleze McKenzie collection of medieval manuscript leaves.
6931
Eleze McKenzie
1.5 cubic feet.
Manuscripts
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Medieval manuscript leaves collected by Eleze McKenzie.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Medieval manuscript leaves collected by Eleze McKenzie. Items are from England, France, Germany, India, Italy, the Low Countries, and Turkey.
Also, photographs of McKenzie and her husband and photographs of the manuscripts on display in her home.
SUBJECTS
Names:
McKenzie, Eleze.
Form and Genre Terms:
Parchment; Illuminated; Vellum; Gothic scripts
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
See also the Medieval manuscript fragments collection, #6532, http://resolver.library.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/EADresolver?id=RMM06532
CONTAINER LIST
- Original manuscript leaf from the Qur'an, 1122 (Box 2)
  Description: Written on both sides of an original leaf of pure vellum with many unusual decorations of a floral design on each page illuminated and heightened in gold on page intialed in red on the opening initial. The bottom margin has been repaired and remargined with 18th century paper. double quarto Cairo 1122. guaranteed to be genuine.
- Leaves from a Book of Hours, c. 1450 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Size: three leaves: one 155x112mm, two 105x72mm
  Description: France.
  Dealer description: For the two smaller: "written in Latin on vellum in an attractive gothic hand in brown ink. Each leaf with a number of decorated initials, some two-line in gold and colours, some one-line in gold or blue with contrasting penwork. Linefillers in gold and colours. Rubrics in red. Each leaf is written and illuminated on both sides, 15 text linesper side. France, c.1450." For the one larger: "Written in Latin on vellum in a firm gothic hand in black ink. Each leaf with a number of decorated initials, one-line in gold or blue, two-line in gold, red & blue. Rubrics in red. Each leaf is written and illuminated on both sides, 17 text lines per side. France, c. 1450."
- MS Leaf, 1408 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Size: 7.25" x 5.25"
  Description: Horae, Atelier de Boucicault. France.
  Dealer description: Leaf from "the Chester Beatty Hours". Paris, 1408. Border on three sides. One leaf on vellum from a Book of Hours written and illuminated in Paris in the year 1408. Has elaborate ivy-leaf borders in gold and colour, plus several initials and decorative line endings.
- South German Artist, c. 1490 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Size: 185mm x 250mm
  Description: Illuminated miniature of the Presentation in the Temple, on a bifolium from a Processional. Southwestern Germany.
  Dealer description: Large historiated initial "L" (75x54mm.) with miniature showing the Virgin on the right passing the Holy Child to a priest wearing a red hooded cloak, with a gothic altar. The initial painted in gold, and set within a coloured frame. Square musical notation on five red 4-line staves, with interlinear text in a gothic hand. A fine illuminated leaf from a manuscript processional which carried the date 1489 (originally in lot 35 in Hartung & Karl's sale, 18 June 1980). It must have been written for a nunnery since the rubrics there referred to "sengerin" and "schuester". The initial introduces the text for the procession for Candelmas on 2 Februrary: "Lumen ad revelationem..." In excellent condition.
- Heures a L'Usage de Paris, c. 1400 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Description: Contains two miniature paintings 1 1/4" in diameter: one of the Virgin Mary with her mother, Saint Ann; the other of Saint Mary Magdalene. France.
  Dealer description: Leaf from a Book of Hours. Paris, late 15th century. Possibly from a printed Book of Hours.
- Biblia Sacra Latina, 13th century (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Size: 11" x 8"
  Description: Manuscript, French (Paris) 13th century. Biblia Sacra Latina. Chapter numerals in red and blue with much penwork ornamentation. The work contained a number of historiated and illuminated initials. Remarkable for the extremely wide margins.
  Dealer description: Leaf from Latin Bible, with historiated initial of Samuel annoting David. 47 lines, double columns.
- Biblia Sacra Latina, 13th century? (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Size: 11.5" x 8"
  Description: Manuscript, French (Paris) 13th century. Biblia Sacra Latina. Initial showing a scene of baptism.
  Dealer description: Leaf from Latin Bible. Paris, 13th century. 47 lines, double columns.
- Leaf from choirbook, c. 1520 (Folder 1)
  Size: 20.5" x 14.75"
  Description: Vellum leaf from a large choir book. Seven lines each of music in square neumes in black ink on red four-line staves and seven lines of text in large gothic script. Rheinland.
  Dealer description: German (Rhenish) Illuminator: c. 1520. Vellum leaf from a large Choir Book. With ornamental intial D containing the head of a bearded man and with a dragon on the outside; and initial E with a man's profile on the outside.
- Flemish Leaf, 1400s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Size: 6.25" x 5"
  Description: Flanders.
  Dealer description: Leaf from Breviary or Missal: Flanders. c. 1450. 30 lines, double columns.
- Dutch illuminator, 15th century (middle) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Size: 156mm x 110mm
  Description: Illuminated leaf on vellum from a Book of Hours in Dutch c. 1450. Netherlands.
  Dealer description: Handsome three-line initial "H" in highly burnished gold on a pink and blue ground with white tracery, bar border in pink, gold and blue, marginal sprays of penwork stems terminating in burnished gold bezants and trefoils; on the verso a similar initial and border. One-line initials in red and blue. 19 lines of text in a gothic hand. In pristine condition.
- Hours of the Virgin, 15th century (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Size: 6.75" x 5.25"
  Description: Use of Sarum in Latin. France.
  Dealer description: Leaf from Book of Hours. France, 15th century (second quarter). 23 lines
- French illuminator, 15th century (3rd quarter) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Size: 180mm x 125mm
  Description: Illuminated MS Leaf on vellum from a Book of Hours. [Paris or Tours?], France, c. 1470.
  Dealer description: On verso fine panel border of flowers and folliage in gold and colours incorporating a bird in brown and pink; on recto another panel border with three sections of thistles, berries and flowers on a gold ground with foliage filling out the remaining areas. One of the 2-line and twelve 1-line initials in gold on a ground of blue and red with white tracery, lines infulled with same colours. 18 lines of text in a gothic hand.
- French Book of Hours, 15th century (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Size: 6.25" x 5.25"
  Description: Original French Manuscript. Probably Diocese of Paris, France.
  Dealer description: Leaf from Book of Hours. France, c. 1450. 13 lines.
- Horae leaf: Use of Sarum, c. 1475 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Size: 7.5" x 5.25"
  Description: Double leaf. Use of Sarum
  Dealer description: Double-leaf from Book of Hours (use of Sarum). C. 1475. 23 lines.
- Illuminated miniature of the Nativity, c. 1480-1490 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Size: 203mm x 247mm
  Description: Rouen artist. Illuminated miniature of the Nativity. France.
  Dealer description: Large rectangular miniature of the Navtivity (117x73mm), showing Mary and Joseph raising their hands and looking down at the Holy Child who lies on the Virgin's cloak, the scene set in an open stable which is partially covered by a red and gold tapestry screen; four shepherds peer in over the fence, landscape background. Decorative border on three sides composed of silver and green acanthus, coloured flowers, daisies and a large bird and a grotesque animal. Ornamental intials and line-fillers. 23 lines of text in lettre batarde. A charming and colourful nativity scene from a Rouen Book of Hours of good quality, with a fascinating border. In excellent condition.
- Bruges artist, c. 1470 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Size: 227mm x 153mm
  Description: Illuminated miniature of the Betrayal of Christ. Bruges, Flanders.
  Dealer description: Historiated initial showing Christ being betrayed by Judas in front of a crowd of soldiers, in the foreground Malchus is having his ear cut off by Peter. The initial painted in blue with white tracery in a gold frame. Border on three sides composed of blue and green acanthus, flowers and fruit and other coloured flowers and leaves, the text contained within a gold and pink border on three sides. 17 lines of gothic text (text area: 146x95mm). Superb illumination from a Book of Hours almost certainly produced in Bruges in the workshop of William Vrelant, probably the most influential artist in Bruges in the second half of the 15th century. It is probably from one of the many manuscripts produced in Bruges for the English market. Another leaf from this manuscript contained a miniature of the commendation of souls, a scene rarely depicted in continental Books of Hours, but much more common in English Books of Hours, or those produced for the English market. The historiated intial introduces lauds. This is from a manuscript of considerable dimensions written in a large liturgical script obviously commissioned by a patron of high rank.
- Arabic Calligrapher, 15th-16th century? (Box 2)
  Description: Manuscript leaf from a Qur'an; written in naskh script.
- Hours of the Virgin, 15th century (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Size: 5.5" x 4.5"
  Description: Use of Sarum in Latin. England.
  Dealer description: Double leaf from Book of Hours (use of Sarum) England, c. 1450.
- French illuminator, c. 1430-1450 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Size: 202mm x 146mm
  Description: Illuminated leaf from a Book of Hours. Northwestern France.
  Dealer description: On each side of the leaf a wide ornamental border composed of gold oak leaves and pink and blue flowers on hair-line stems which radiate from a bar border of pink and burnished gold. 3 two-line initials in pink and blue on burnished gold grounds and 5 one-line initials on pink and blue grounds, two line-fillers. 15 lines of Gothic text in brown ink. A very attractive leaf with the text completely surrounded by the border decoration on the recto and with a three-sided border on the verso. In excellent condition.
- Italian illuminator, c. 1450 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Size: 280mm x 195mm
  Description: Illuminated bifolium from a Book of Hours. Northeastern Italy, c. 1450.
  Dealer description: Beautiful 6-line illuminated initial 'S' painted on a burnished gold ground in pink, green and orange acanthus, with full length marginal extension of lush blue, pink and orange acanthus on a gold ground, gold bezants and a long-legged bird drawn in two colours in lower margin; red and blue initials. 18 lines of text in a rounded gothic hand. A beautifully illuminated bifolium from a Book of Hours of high quality, remarkable for the lush foliage decoration. Probably from N.E. Italy (perhaps Ferrara).
- Leaf from Book of Hours, 1452 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Size: 5.5" x 4"
  Description: Flemish.
  Dealer description: Handwritten provenance history: "310 pages. 6 illuminated (1 w/miniatures). Floriated borders, Burnished gold paint. Lapis Lazure Blue paint. From the Duc de Lilchtenstein's Library. 1800's - sold at auction to an Austrian library (state operated) 1800's - sold to a p'vt collector (European) 1900's (incomplete) - sold to an Antique Bookdealer 1964 (incomplete) - sold to an American collector 1965 (incomplete) - sold to an American collector" Leaf from Flemish Book of Hours. c. 1450. With 10-line illuminated capital.
- Hours of the Virgin, 15th century (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Size: 5.75" x 4.25"
  Description: Calendar page. Miniature painting, Northern France; illuminated manuscript.
  Dealer description: Leaf from Book of Hours. N. France, c. 1480-1500. 15 lines.
- Indian miniature, 19th century (Box 2)
  Description: Script: Sanskrit, from the Bhagurad Gita.
  Dealer description: Krishna with his two loves: cows and women.
- Turkish manuscript (Box 2)
  Description: Turkish Qur'an.
- Manuscript Brevary in Latin (of St. Victor), 15th century (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Size: 6.75" x 4.75"
  Description: Breviary. Flemish. MS in Latin of St. Victor.
  Dealer description: Leaf from Flemish Breviary c. 1450-70. 18 lines.
- Hours of the Virgin, 15th century (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Size: 6.25" x 4.5"
  Description: Use of Sarum in Latin. MS leaf. France.
  Dealer description: Leaf from Book of Hours. France, c. 1460. 13 lines.
- Minuscule Bible leaf, c. 1150? (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Description: Britain, in Latin, uterine vellum.
  Dealer description: Leaf from Latin Bible. England, 13th century. 47 lines, double columns (Ecclesiastes).
- Horae. Calendar Leaf., 15th century (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Dealer description: Leaf from Book of Hours. France. c. 1470.
- Turkish manuscript, 1820-1840 (Box 2)
- Illuminated leaf from a Psalter, c. 1300 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Description: Flanders, France.
- MS Leaf in Dutch, 15th century (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Size: 4.5" x 3.25"
  Description: Netherlands.
  Dealer description: Leaf from Book of Hours in Dutch c. 1450. 16 lines.
- Flemish Illuminator, c. 1240 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Size: 128mm x 90mm
  Description: Low Countries. Illuminted leaf from a Psalter. Flanders.
  Dealer description: Thick blue and mauve border with 6 initials in burnished gold, red and blue line-filler (on both recto and verson). 19 lines of early gothic script in black ink. Very attractive leaf from a pocket-sized psalter.
- Manuscript leaf, c. 1400 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Size: 4.25" x 3.75"
  Dealer description: Calendar leaf from Book of Hours. France, c. 1460. 17 lines.
- Photographs, c. 1940s-1960s (Box 72, Folder m6931)
  Description: McKenzie, her husband, and the manuscripts on display in her home.